A Guide to the Henrico County (Va.) Maps, Plats, Plans and Drawings, 1806-1954
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Henrico County (Va.) Maps, Plats, Plans and Drawings, 1806-1954
The Library of Virginia
1177420-1177422
2 cu. ft. (2 boxes) and 1 map drawer
Henrico County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court papers from Henrico County.
Alternative Form Available
Some of these items, particularly the land plats and surveys, may be recorded in the Henrico County Plat Books which are available on microfilm on Henrico County (Va.) Reels 114, 178-181.
Historical Information
Recognized in 1634 as an original shire. All county court records prior to 1655 and almost all prior to 1677 are missing. Many records were destroyed by British troops during the Revolutionary War. Post–Revolutionary War county court records exist. Almost all circuit superior court of law and chancery and circuit court records were destroyed by fire during the evacuation of Richmond on April 3, 1865, during the Civil War. The county’s circuit court held its sessions at the state courthouse in Richmond.
Scope and Content
Henrico County (Va.) Maps, Plats, Plans and Drawings, 1806-1954, consist of loose maps, plats, surveys, plans, drawings and blueprints located in the several series that compose the records of Henrico County at the Library of Virginia.
Land Records include any map, survey, plat, or plan that was made in connection with a land transaction, estate settlement, or court case.
Road and Bridge Records include any map, survey, plat, drawing or plan that was produced in connection with a Richmond City, Henrico County, or state of Virginia road or bridge project. Some of the documents relate to improvements along the canal in Richmond.
N.B. This finding aid is part of an ongoing project to process and catalog the Henrico County maps and plats in the Library of Virginia's archival holdings. It will be updated from time to time.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following local records series: Land Records and Road and Bridge Records.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Henrico County land records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
Henrico County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Henrico County Court Records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the Lost Records Localities Database found at the Library of Virginia web site.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Henrico County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
Land tenure--Virginia--Henrico County.; Land use surveys--Virginia--Henrico County.; Roads--Design and construction.
Geographical Names:
Henrico County (Va.)--History.; Virginia--Maps.
Genre and Form Terms:
Historical maps--Virginia--Henrico County.; Land surveys--Virginia--Henrico County.; Land use maps--Virginia--Henrico County.; Local government records--Virginia--Henrico County.; Manuscript maps--Virginia--Henrico County.; Plans (maps)--Virginia--Henrico County.; Plats--Virginia--Henrico County.
Contents List
- Land Records: 1806-1921
  Includes maps, plats and surveys of land that may be related to estate settlements, deeds, exhibits in a court case, or as an advertisement for land sales. Some of the documents are for land that falls outside of Henrico County or is for property that once was part of Henrico but now falls within the city limits of Richmond.
  - [Fragments (2) of surveyor text description of an unidentified tract of land], 1844 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Notes: Mentions Reedy/Ready Creek.
  - [171 1/2 acres belonging to John George Esq.], 1850 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Notes: Adjoining lands labeled as the Cider Mill tract, and belonging to Goodman, Lindsey, and Childress.
  - Lee Annex, Richmond, VA, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Notes: By T. Crawford Redd showing Kensington St. to Monument Ave. and Roseneath Rd. to Sheppard St.
  - Sundry lotts belonging to the estate of Wiltshire M. Lewis, 1812 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Notes: Showing Rocketts Mills, Gilleys Creek, Rocketts Bridge, Rocketts St., Poplar St., Ash St., Elm St., and County or River Rd.
  - Plan of sundry lots adjoining the city of Richmond formerly the property of Col. Richard Adams and purchased by Dr. John Adams and Benjamin Mosby, 1813 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Notes: Subscribers apppointed by order of Prince Edward Co. to divide estate of Abraham Venable have further proceeded to a division of the unimproved lots in City of Richmond belonging to estate of A. B. Venable comveyed to him by Adams, December 13, 1805.
  - Plat for lots for Philip Haxall (fragments), 1814 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - George Greenhow's plat of lots number two, 1815 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Notes: City of Richmond by Richard Young, surveyor City of Richmond.....on the road leading from Richmond by Fairfield to the meadow bridges....road leading from Richmond through the Bowling Green towards the Meadow bridges.
  - Plan of ten lots of land surveyed for Anderson Barret, they being a part of his tract of land lying between the Westham Road and James River, 1816 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Notes: On reverse: 1818 August produced in court and ordered recorded; plot, advertisement, and sale of Anderson Barret land.
  - Plan of lots at Rocketts, 1819 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Notes: Adjoining Water Street late the property of John Banks, by Richard Young. Possibly related to Alexander Fulton and the Marion Hill Company.
  - [Map of Powhatan (1826)] estate of William Mayo 1826 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Notes: This map not conserved. See conserved copy in Map Cabinet 7 Drawer 4.
  - Surveyed at the instance of James Talley a tract of land situate near the said city [of Richmond], 1831 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Notes: Showing Mechanicksville Turnpike Rd. and plan of the Bowling Green village.
  - Survey of a tract....called....Cockermouth as sold under directions of the court by Samuel P. Parsons, Commissioner, 1835 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Notes: Showing James River, Charles City Rd., Darby Rd., racefield.
  - A map of Bremo surveyed at the instance of William N. Whiting, 1837 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Notes: Showing James River to east, Hog-Pen Creek, Bremo Creek.
  - A map of Westbrook belonging to estate of William Young. 1838 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Notes: Showing Richmond and Fredericksburg Railroad, Brook Turnpike, Brook schoolhouse, Brook Run.
  - A portion of the "Fair Field" tract of land near this City which has been surveyed and divided into lots at the request of James Talley and Robert New, 1840 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Notes: Includes lot numbers and acerage.
  - Survey of land in Buchanan's Old Field belonging to the estate of John Graham, 1840 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Notes: Includes lot numbers and names of purchasers. Showing J St. to Brook Rd. and Pine St.
  - New Market Tract of land, 1846 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Notes: Belonging to Susan H. Sharpe.
  - Plat of several parcels of land purchased by J. B. Bragg lying in Henrico County about 3 miles below Richmond and containing in the aggregate 414,680 acres, 1858, In two pieces with some pieces missing. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Notes: Showing the New Charles City Rd. and names of grantors with acreage.
  - Map of Part No. 2 laid off to C. W. Purcell and Bacon [text missing] in the division of Fairfield by the Commissioners....filed in the office of circuit court of Henrico in suit of Purcell etc. vs. Tall[ey], 1859, Piece with text missing from the surveyor's description. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Brook Estate....of the late Nathaniel Crenshaw in accordance with his will, 1866, 1 plat on sheet with 3 related others. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Woodland directed by Nathaniel C. Crenshaw's will to be added to the Brook Estate, 1866, 3 plats on sheet with 1 related other. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Map of a portion of the estate of Turkey Island as divided between the heirs of the late Col. R. Pickett, 1868 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Notes: Showing James River, Turkey Island Creek, Charles City Rd.
  - Plan of Arlington, in Sydney, near Richmond, 1872 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Notes: Showing Ashland St. to Harvie St. and Robinson St. to [Carter] St. Laid out for Mr. Charles M. Wallace...to be sold at auction...by Alexander Y. Lee, architect and civil engineer.
  - Map of "Hermitage Park" in Henrico County, VA, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Notes: Hermitage Land Company, owners. By T. C. Redd and Bro. Marked Exhibit A: E. A. Catlin, 1914, Patterson vs. Patterson.
  - Plan of Northampton adjoining Ginter Park, Henrico County, VA, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Notes: By T. Crawford Redd and Bro. Rolled inside another map marked as an exhibit in Patterson vs. Patterson.
  - Map of R. A. Patterson estate, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Notes: Showing "Reveille," Leonard Heights, Monument Heights. By T. Crawford Redd and Bro. On reverse marked: Filed with commissioner Gardner's report May 27, 1914 Patterson vs. Patterson, exhibit C.P.E.B. number 2.
  - [Section showing Louisiana and Orleans streets from river to 8th and the county road with land of George M. Carrington and R. A. Mayo], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Locust Hill owned by Garland Hanes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Notes: Surveyed by James T. Redd.
  - Map of an extention of Rutherfoord's plan upon the property of Valentine Heckler, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Notes: Showing 25th to 28th streets and Venable (or Q) St. to the county road.
  - A plan of Woodville, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Notes: Showing Mechanicksville Turnpike Rd. and the toll house.
  - [Plat showing Louisiana St. and 2nd, 3rd, 6th, 7th and 8th streets to the county road], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - The Town of Sydney, 1806/1817 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: plat of the land allotted to J. B. Harvie by William Brockenbrough, Thomas Taylor and Robert Gamble, commissioners appointed by the Superior Court of Chancery to divide the land between the said Harvie and the representatives of [illegible] Edwin James Harvie, deceased.
  - A map of part of the Hermitage Tract belonging to Col. John Mayo situated south of the Richmond Turnpike Rd., 1816 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: Showing Scuffletown, Westham Rd., street in line with F St. by Richard Young, surveyor City of Richmond.
  - The Town of Sydney, 1817 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: a plat of the land alotted to J. B. Harvie by William Brockenbrough, Thomas Taylor and Robert Gamble, commissioners appointed by the Superior Court of Chancery to divide the land between the said Harvie and the representatives of his brother Edwin James Harvie, deceased.
  - Surveyed at the request of Col. Thomas H. Prosser a tract or parcel of land....on the north run of the Brook....and contains by survey 978 acres, 1818 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: Showing Rocky Branch, North Run of the Brook, new road to the Pitts, Brook Turnpike, Owens Tavern, lot owner's names.
  - Plan of Marion Hill, 1819 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: Showing Harris to McCoull streets, Fisher to Almond streets and the James River, Academy, and some names of lot owners. Note: 1819 November 3rd presented in court by Alexander Fulton, trustee for the Marion Hill Company.
  - Map of Powhatan, estate of William Mayo, deceased, 1826 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: Shows Powhatan mansion house and family burying ground, James River, street names to north and west.
  - Surveyed at the instance of Captain George Booker, superintendent of the Richmond Dock Companyfor the said company the lands w[h]ere on the said dock is erected and such as is contemplated to be condemned by virtue of a write of ad quod damnum.... 1827 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: By Richard Young. Showing Mayo's Bridge east to Peach St., D St. to docks and Cripple Island or Sandy Bar Fishery.
  - Annexed plat of survey is taken from actual survey made by me at sundry times as well as that of Chappell Island as that part of the city of Richmond thereunto immediately adjoining at the instance of Edward Hinshaw, 1828 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: By Richard Young. Showing 15th St. east to 22nd St., D St. with canal to docks of Richmond Dock Company.
  - 206 acres in Charles City Co. adjoining Batchelor's Point surveyed by request of William B. Harrison of Prince George Co. by William Clopton, surveyor of Henrico Co., 1844 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: Includes Edward Colgin's estate called Batchelor's Point and James River.
  - [Plat accompanying report of surveyor dated October 17, 1848, from Richmond City Superior Court of Chancery cause Hall Neilson vs. Edward C. Mayo], 1848 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: By Micajah Bates. Includes surveyor's report. Showing islands in the James River from Broad Rock Island to Long Island and Mayo Bridge.
  - [Plat accompanying report of surveyor dated October 17, 1848, from Richmond City Superior Court of Chancery cause Hall Neilson vs. Edward C. Mayo], 1848, DO NOT SERVE--too fragile. Serve conserved copy in Map Cabinet 7 Drawer 4. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Map of the lands of the West-End Land and Improvement Company, 1889 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: By James T. Redd and Sons. Showing Crenshaw Ave. to Lombardy St. and Richmond College; Broad St. to Reservoir Park and Beverley St.
  - Section No. I, 1906, Encapsulated. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: By W. E. Cutshaw, city engineer, for circuit court cases City of Richmond vs. County of Henrico and Atkinson vs. City of Richmond and County of Henrico. Showing James River, Maymont, Shield's Grove, Mt. Calvary Cemetery, Virginia Union University, Hartshorn College, Old Fairgrounds, Richmond Union Stockyards, Spruce St., Nelson St., Crenshaw Ave. to Randolph and Oak St., "Old Corporation Line" and "New Corporation Line."
  - [Proposed development at Cary Street Rd. and Lock Rd. with estate of A. W. Patterson], 1914 ca. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: written on reverse: Patterson vs. Patterson. Exhibit: Gillette, with stamped date May 20, 1914. Filed with Commissioner Gardner's report. Probably drawn by Charles Gillette.
  - Subdivision of Section "D" Fairfield, Henrico Co., VA, 1921, Blueprint. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: Property of Richmond Fairfield Railway Co. Showing section along Nine Mile Rd. and Williamsburg Rd.
- Road and Bridge Records: 1828-1954
  Includes blueprints, maps, and plats for road, bridge, and canal improvements in and around Henrico County undertaken by various agencies.
  - Plat of 1 acre taken for the use of James......House etc. bounded as appears....surveyed September 15, 178[?], 1828, One of four small plats on one sheet. Sheet is torn into two pieces with some text loss. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Notes: Original of this plat sent James Brown Jr., Second Auditor, by William H. Brown, 14th June 1828 per order filed, Lofton N. Ellett, CHC. By Elliot Lacy, Surveyor G. C.
  - Plat of the canal containing 22 acres land belonging to Francis Watkins, certified under my hand this 17th day May 1786, 1828, One of four small plats on one sheet. Sheet is torn into two pieces with some text loss. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Notes: By Elliot Lacy, surveyor G. C. Original of this plat sent James Brown Jr., Second Auditor, by William H. Brown, 14th June 1828 per order filed, Lofton N. Ellett, CHC.
  - Plat of lands surveyed for the use of the canal belonging to McCaul & Trent, 1828, One of four small plats on one sheet. Sheet is torn into two pieces with some text loss. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Notes: By Elliot Lacy, surveyor G. C. "The contents you may see by the above plot, Surveyed June 2d, 1786." Original of this plat sent James Brown Jr., Second Auditor, by William H. Brown, 14th June 1828 per order filed, Lofton N. Ellett, CHC.
  - Plat of 10 3/4 acres land for use of James & Samuel Overton....and running down the courses....1786, 1828, One of four small plats on one sheet. Sheet is torn into two pieces with some text loss. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Map of Henrico County, Virginia, 1918, Blueprint. (Map-case 7, Drawer 4)
    Notes: red lines show tentative county highway system; yellow lines show state highway system.
  - Plan showing a proposed road 50 feet wide extending from the Hermitage Rd. to the Broad Street Rd., 1906, Blueprint. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: By T. Crawford Redd & Bro. On reverse written: Acca Station, Board of Supervisors Henrico Co. in the matter of petition of Jos. Bryan for improvement of road passing Acca Station. Map #2 with report of views.
  - Plan showing a proposed road 50 feet wide extending from the Hermitage Rd. to the Broad Street Rd., 1906, Blueprint. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: By T. Crawford Redd & Bro. Rolled with another map titled "Plat of the country road, continuation of Westwood Ave...." and housed in same folder.
  - Plat of the country road, continuation of Westwood Ave., showing a proposed widening of same, and also a bridge over the Richmond Fredericksburg and Potomac Railroad at Acca, 1906, Blueprint. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: By T. Crawford Redd & Bro. Rolled with another map titled "Plan showing a proposed road 50 feet wide...." and housed in same folder.
  - [3 maps showing plans for constructing the canal and improvements in the James River affecting the property of Dutch Gap Land Corporation, Phillip N. Stoneman, and Albert B. Ruddock], 1931 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: by Richmond Department of Public Works. One map for each property affected.
  - Proposed sewer lines and proposed profiles of streets in Dickensdale Section B, Henrico Co., VA, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes: Stapled onto map: a paper reading: Defendant exhibit (3) Fleet. Filed June 24, 1958.